Guide to the Rice Hotel memorabilia collection, ca. 1913-1977 UA 241
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice Hotel memorabilia collection
1913-1977
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice Hotel (Houston, Tex.)
UA 241
8.5 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
This collection consists of Rice Hotel (Houston, Tex.) memorabilia and includes menus, drink lists, advertising material, and stationery. Included are a 1913 dinner plate, china and silverplate. In 1886 William Marsh Rice bought the old Capitol Hotel, built in 1882, for unpaid taxes. Rice University obtained the hotel as a bequest from its owner and renamed it the Rice Hotel. Jesse H. Jones purchased the building in 1911, and in 1913 tore it down and replaced it with a new Rice Hotel. The hotel closed in 1977, but the structure was later redesigned as luxury "loft" apartments and reopened in 1988. (1 box)
Biographical / Historical
In 1886, William Marsh Rice bought the old Capitol Hotel, built in 1882, for unpaid taxes. Rice University obtained the hotel as a bequest from its owner and renamed it the Rice Hotel. Jesse H. Jones purchased the building in 1911, and in 1913 tore it down and replaced it with a new Rice Hotel. The hotel closed in 1977, but the structure was later redesigned as luxury "loft" apartments and reopened in 1988.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of hotel memorabilia and includes menus, drink lists, advertising material, and stationery. Included are a 1913 dinner plate, pieces of additional china and silverplate.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received in part from Lee Pecht, 1999 and Greg Marshall, November 2000, and at auction in 2014. Additional material received from Houston Endowment in Dec. 2017.
Index Terms
Subjects
Sports; Universities and colleges; Social life and customs
Document Types
memorabilia
- Series I: Memorabilia, 159940
  - Large dinner menu, 159941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Flag Room" menu cover, 159942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Flag Room" menu, 159943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rice Hotel drink list, 159944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Convention invitation folder, featuring a description of the Rice Hotel logo which included the 6 flags over Texas and the wording "Rice Hotel: Houston's Traditional Host", 159945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Rice Roomer," Vol. 1, No. 1 (undated): breakfast menu, wine cellar list, advertisements, 159946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Convention" brochure, with color images of interior spaces for conventions, ca. 1965, 159947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2 blue hotel brochures, with full color images of interior and exterior amentities, ca. 1970s, 159948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Welcome to the Rice" booklet of services, ca. 1960s, 159949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hotel stationery and envelopes, undated, various versions of hotel logo; includes first day of issue for the Sam Houston stamp with drawings of Capitol Hotel and Rice Hotel "mailed from The Rice Hotel, site of the first capitol of the Republic of Texas", 159950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Old Capitol Club "guest" cards, 159951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Rice Crispies" Secretarial Club card, 159952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rice Hotel room key, 159953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rice Hotel matchbook, 159954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rice Hotel pewter bowl, 159955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rice Hotel metal drink server, 159957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - clay brick shard from west exterior face, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Rice Hotel small oval glass serving tray with Rice Hotel crest (Box 2)
  - Rice Hotel dinner plate, 1913 (Box 2)
  - Rice Hotel construction #15, framed (Box 3)
  - Rice Hotel construction #24, framed (Box 3)
  - Rice Hotel Laundry employees, framed (Box 3)
  - Rice Hotel seal on glass card trays (2) (Box 4)
  - Water glass (Box 4)
  - Rice Hotel china
    - Dinner plate with flags motif (chipped) (Box 4)
    - Soup bowl, large (Box 4)
    - Serving bowl, oval, medium (Box 4)
    - Relish dish (Box 4)
    - Demi-tasse cups (2) (Box 4)
    - Salad plate (2) (Box 5)
    - Bread/butter plate (Box 5)
    - Bowl, medium (Box 5)
    - Bowl, small (Box 5)
    - Saucer (Box 5)
    - Coffee cups (2) (Box 5)
    - Creamer with handle, small (Box 5)
    - Creamer, no handle, small (Box 5)
  - Rice Hotel silverplate
    - Platter, oval, small, imprinted "The Rice;" Reed & Barton (Box 6)
    - Bowl, square, small, imprinted "The Rice;" Reed & Barton (Box 6)
    - Candle sticks, pair [had been electrified for lamps], "Smith Silver Co., Bridgeport, Conn." (Box 6)
    - Serving dish, oval, small, Reed & Barton (Box 6)
    - Tableware: dinner knife, serving spoon; with "The Rice" markings-dinner fork, pickle fork, iced tea spoon, small soup spoon, teaspoons (2) (Box 6)
  - Metal door plates & knobs (2) (Box 6)
  - Metal pitcher, small, "Rice Hotel Quality Aluminum Ware" (Box 6)
  - Printer's block, "Rice Hotel" (Box 6)
  - Rice Hotel silverplate
    - Sugar bowl with cover, small, Reed & Barton (Box 7)
    - Serving platter with cover, small (Box 7)
    - Platter cover, large (Box 7)
  - Rice Hotel plaque for room 1417 (with gargoyle) for hallway identification (Box 8)
  - Rice Hotel crest (metal) mounted on board (Box 9)
  - Rice Hotel bell hop uniforms (2), jacket & pants (Box 10)